http://stackoverflow.com/questions/10060411/byte-string-vs-unicode-string-python

byte string vs. unicode string. Python

No python does not use its own encoding. It will use any encoding that it has access to and that you specify. A character in a str represents one unicode character. However to represent more than 256 characters, individual unicode encodings use more than one byte per character to represent many characters. bytearray objects give you access to the underlaying bytes. str objects have the encode method that takes a string representing an encoding and returns the bytearray object that represents the string in that encoding. bytearray objects have the decode method that takes a string representing an encoding and returns the str that results from interpreting the bytearray as a string encoded in the the given encoding. Here's an example.

>>> a = "αά".encode('utf-8')
>>> a
b'\xce\xb1\xce\xac'
>>> a.decode('utf-8')
'αά'

We can see that UTF-8 is using four bytes, \xce, \xb1, \xce, and \xac to represent two characters. After the Spolsky article that Ignacio Vazquez-Abrams referred to, I would read the Python Unicode Howto [http://docs.python.org/release/3.2/howto/unicode.html].


# Note:

MINGW64 ~
$ python -i
Python 2.7.11 (v2.7.11:6d1b6a68f775, Dec  5 2015, 20:40:30) [MSC v.1500 64 bit (AMD64)] on win32
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>> a = u"αά".encode('utf-8')
>>> a
'\xc3\x8e\xc2\xb1\xc3\x8e\xc2\xac'
>>>

http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3828723/why-should-we-not-use-sys-setdefaultencodingutf-8-in-a-py-script

Why should we NOT use sys.setdefaultencoding("utf-8") in a py script?

As per the documentation: This allows you to switch from the default ASCII to other encodings such as UTF-8, which the Python runtime will use whenever it has to decode a string buffer to unicode.

This function is only available at Python start-up time, when Python scans the environment. It has to be called in a system-wide module, sitecustomize.py, After this module has been evaluated, the setdefaultencoding() function is removed from the sys module.

The only way to actually use it is with a reload hack that brings the attribute back.

Also, the use of sys.setdefaultencoding() has always been discouraged, and it has become a no-op in py3k. The encoding of py3k is hard-wired to "utf-8" and changing it raises an error.

I suggest some pointers for reading:

• http://blog.ianbicking.org/illusive-setdefaultencoding.html
• http://nedbatchelder.com/blog/200401/printing_unicode_from_python.html
• http://www.diveintopython3.net/strings.html#one-ring-to-rule-them-all
• http://boodebr.org/main/python/all-about-python-and-unicode
• http://blog.notdot.net/2010/07/Getting-unicode-right-in-Python